"Golden vs Brown Flaxseed:
Which Has More Benefits?"
Embellished as a so-called
miraculous defense
against some critical maladies,
flaxseeds are one
of the original health foods,
going back thousands of years
to the time of Hippocrates.
You can buy them in bulk
for about three bucks a pound,
which would last you
nearly two months
at the one-tablespoon-a-day dose
I recommend
in my Dr. Greger's
Daily Dozen app.
Flaxseeds come with
nature's own finest packaging:
a hard natural hull
that keeps them fresh inside.
Unfortunately,
nature's packaging
is a little too good.
If we eat flaxseeds whole,
they are likely to just pass
right through us,
come out the other end,
and not do us much good.
So, chew them really well,
or grind them
in a coffee or spice grinder,
a mini food processor,
a good blender,
or just buy them
already ground.
Ground flaxseeds can be stored
for months at room temperature
in an airtight container.
Ground flaxseeds have
a nice binding quality
that makes for thick, rich
milkshake-y-type smoothies.
In fact, you can use
ground flaxseeds
to replace eggs in baking.
For each egg in a recipe,
blend one tablespoon
of ground flax
with three tablespoons of water
until it gets all gooey.
With that swap, you'd be
actively lowering cholesterol--
based on more than five dozen
randomized controlled trials--
rather than raising it
as the eggs would've.
There are brown flaxseeds
and golden flaxseeds.
Brown ones may have
about 20 percent more omega-3s
than golden,
but, like, 30% more
antioxidant power.
They both lower blood pressures
similarly,
but golden flax appears better
at lowering cholesterol levels.
Both golden and brown
helped seal a leaky gut,
but brown seems better
at reducing endotoxemia.
Far as I'm concerned,
brown wins,
because brown flaxseed
beats out golden
with 60 percent more lignans,
those anticancer compounds
activated by our gut flora.
That's the main reason
ground flax is better
than flaxseed oil, in addition
to being more stable.
Ground flaxseeds don't oxidize
even after nearly a year
at room temperature
in an airtight container,
presumably because they are
packed with antioxidants.
But strip those away
to make flaxseed oil,
and it can start to turn rancid
within a matter of weeks.
The lignans are also
stripped away in flax oil.
If you look at the ingredients
of so-called "high lignan"
flaxseed oils, it's a scam.
They just sprinkle in
some ground flax into the oil
to add a pittance.
Lignans are why flaxseeds
are so powerful
at dampening
the effects of estrogen.
Eating just a single tablespoon
of ground flaxseeds a day
extends the length
of a woman's menstrual cycle--
not the menses itself,
but the whole month-long cycle--
by an average of about one day.
Beyond improving ovulation
and reducing
common PMS symptoms
such as breast pain
and cramping,
the lengthening of the cycle
means you have fewer periods
throughout your life,
which means
less estrogen exposure
and lower breast cancer risk.
Lignans may explain
why flaxseed consumption
is associated with a lower risk
of getting breast cancer
and dying from it,
whereas greater antibiotic use
is associated
with an increased risk
of getting and dying
from breast cancer,
presumably because antibiotics
can wipe out
some of the good bacteria
in our colon
that activate
the anticancer activity
of flaxseed lignans.
Check out my videos
on preventing
and treating breast cancer
with flax.
Flax is good for men, too,
improving enlarged
prostate symptoms
comparable to common drugs
that are used,
that can cause a wide array
of adverse side effects
including impotence,
whereas the side effects
of flax
are not only lower cholesterol,
but better blood pressures,
better blood sugars,
and maybe fewer hot flashes,
though that's not
usually a big problem
in sufferers
of enlarged prostates.